so when is the last time you served um
like with you
oh that first that first video we made
what i want you now to focus on is that
every time you practice
you involve the serve like if you have
to hit at least i would say 10 to 15
percent of your practice
devoted to the serve and then the serve
will grow along with the rest of your
game okay so let me just see a couple of
surf refresh my memory
that's not bad actually it's not bad at
all
start with the racket in front and shift
your weight onto the front foot
and you can put the ball against your
strings or against the racket throat
like this so i want you to start the
serve
like this every time okay and then i go
back all right so now
the next step is you're going to
separate the toss arm from the racket
arm
and here's how you're gonna do it so
you're going to separate the toss arm
from the racket arm by going back with
the racket arm first you're not going to
toss right away but you're going to go
back with the racket arm first
and then you're going to toss okay
i'll do it again okay so the reason why
i want you to do that because i want to
build a little bit more of a backswing
into your serve
so if you go straight up here this
shortens this this backswing because if
you have a little bit longer
take back on the serve it can give you
more power so look again go here
wait on the bottom wait here toss the
ball and then go at it
okay now racket will go here like this
now you're gonna toss and then you're
gonna hit it
okay and take your time make sure the
toss goes up first you don't have to
rush this part look
here's one two three and then you go
like that okay now when you toss the
ball you have to throw it more in front
in this case you're not going to be
using your body that much so you can
toss it
right along the baseline okay so this is
where you're positioning if you throw
the ball behind you it's not going to be
good
you're going to make contact behind your
head
okay what i don't like about that you're
going up too quickly you're rushing
everything so you're going here
and you're going like this see what i
want you to do is again
one is here two is here three is here
you see this
yeah two three is here there you go hit
it
and then hit two three
and hit there you go much better always
do a grip check see there's
there are several things that you can do
correct every single time you serve
because these are the things that are
happening
before you even start the motion that is
your stance that is how you hold the
racket those things you can get right
every single time and now you're in a
forehand grip
go slightly over there you go now you're
in a continental grip there you go
what do you what do you think about that
toss was it
here or was it behind you no it was
right up yeah it was not actually it was
actually over here behind me it was
behind you
so some people have a hard time knowing
where the toss was
they kind of get disoriented yeah
because the body position will change
sometimes so you lose orientation so you
might think
it was in front of you right because
you're adjusting your body to the bad
toss you might throw it behind now
you're adjusting so it appears
it appears that it's in front of you
however it's only in front of you
because your body moved backwards right
in relation to the baseline the ball was
back here
so always toss and take the bass line as
the orientation
so you want to throw the ball in this
instance because you're not using your
body you're not leaning in you want to
toss the ball
along the baseline okay
wow one two
all right let me tell you a couple of
things about the toss itself so
you don't want to flick the ball up
you're already doing a lot of good
things
naturally with the toss i think because
you're a dancer
and your arm is very elegantly going up
so this is where you get
you have a lot of advantages over other
people but i can see that you're kind of
doing a weird hand movement at the very
end so make sure you you don't do that
when you release the ball have the hand
very still
what i like is having the fingers closer
together upon the release
it's going to help you get a cleaner
toss yeah i feel like i held it
yeah don't don't don't hold it too long
there it is beautiful serve so when i
hit the ball
i'm on the front foot that's a great i
move right yeah that's a great question
i was actually
i was actually going to do the next
progression which is i want you to
rotate into the serve so you're kind of
staying sideways now
and the arm is going forward by itself
so i want you to allow the body to come
with the arm so you're going to have
your shoulders come with
the racket well actually what's going to
happen later on you're actually going to
get airborne
that's going to be later on we're too
early in the surf development to
work on that but eventually you're going
to get up into the air and land inside
the cord
but for now just shift your weight
forward you jump the whole body it's not
really a jump
it's more of a pat what i call a passive
jump the body propels
the legs off the ground if you set
certain parameters on the serve
naturally your body will lift off the
ground it's really fascinating
and we'll do that later on we'll
definitely add that to you sir but it's
too early for that for now all i want
you to do is
go forward with your torso meaning that
you're going to rotate forward you're
going to go up here
and then rotate forward now naturally as
you do that the weight is going to shift
onto your front foot and you can allow
that to happen it's okay
the toss was too low see a lot of
recreational players especially at the
entry level they
find a very big comfort in throwing the
ball low because they know they can make
contact right here close to them they
feel the safety in that
they're kind of scared to throw the ball
too high because then the timing is a
little more difficult but i want you to
ignore
this intuition you have with the low
toss and start tossing the ball
much higher from day one a higher toss
is always better you can always correct
our toss is too high but you can never
correct the toss that's too low because
you will not will not be able to extend
the arm you'll hit it like this
all right and overall you'll rush your
serve too when it's low
you'll speed everything up
much better
much better you see that yeah now one
thing that i noticed as you were
rotating you started
pushing through the ball the arm was
going like that
and that's not a good thing because
you'll hit a lot of balls long if you
hit them hard
so i want you to focus on getting your
hand towards your left pocket if you
imagine if you had a left pocket that's
your right pocket
left pocket so your hand needs to go
towards your left
pocket right here and that's going to
guarantee you that you have more of a
downward
swing
one thing i want you to remember is that
when you release the ball
not to drop the toss arm so fast so you
sometimes do this look
you release and you drop it right away
so this has a bad effect on your
biomechanics on the server but what's
going to happen is if you
keep the toss arm up after you release
the ball it's going to put your body
in a tilt and this tilt is going to be
reversed when you accelerate
which called the cartwheeling effect so
look if i
stay up with my toss arm after the
release you see how my shoulders are
tilted
and now when i accelerate this tilt is
going to reverse and i'm going to be
like this
this is the car yeah it's the
cartwheeling movement
if you drop the toss arm super fast
look if you go up here and then you drop
look my shoulders are level
and i don't get this tilt that i need so
make sure that you don't drop too fast
it
helps you here it helps of course so
once you release it keep that toss arm
up a little bit longer
okay now something happens every time i
give a player this tip to keep the toss
i'm longer right away the toss starts
going behind
this is very very common right i say
keep it up long and all of a sudden
they're throwing it like way
behind them so you have to figure out a
way to release it at the proper point
and then continue going up which is
tricky but look watch me
you see how i continue going up after i
released it and the ball still went in
front
oh that was so good but you didn't go
after it you waited too long
i think it was upfront you know it's not
a bad thing actually this is what i want
you to do eventually
is throw the ball in front and you're
gonna start using your entire body to
hit the serve
so if it does go in front don't you
still hit it that's actually a really
good thing i'm just making you throw it
right here because we're not using the
body fully yet we're just kind of
stationary and serving but eventually
you're going to have to throw it in
front
okay
oh yes wow what a serve
i feel like i just don't overthink
things no no no
don't overthink this is why even when
i'm building your serve now it's like
step by step
i don't want to throw everything at you
with building it step by step
so your body can remember it otherwise
you get information overload and
especially in the case of the serve
because it's so
complex there's so many moving parts
there's so many different things
happening using both
both hands it's very easy to have too
many things in your head
so we're going to keep it simple okay
we're going to go step by step the thing
is like you're teaching me
step by step i learned from the big
concept
smaller so oh that's interesting good
approach
it's really not good for me but that's
the only way to learn to serve
if i if i start teaching you like a
professional grade serve right off the
bat
it's going to be a disaster we have to
show me a few
okay sure i'll show you i'll show you a
serve but when it comes to like building
the serve you got to trust me
that i'm giving you the right
information because
no problem i'll show you as many as you
want
well so there's no way for you to
replicate that because number one
wait it's happening way too fast i'm
just predicting the future i'm
predicting the future right
just wait all right go ahead replicate
what i just did
go ahead let me see
all right so you just you just destroyed
your serve but the reason why you can't
replicate what i just did
is number one the entire set of
fundamentals in in there and there
there's
multiple things that are going on okay
not only that but they're executing with
such speed
that you can't even catch half of the
things that are happening okay
so this is why it's important like i
said before to build the serve step by
step
and we don't and this is also why i'm
not having you use your body yet
we're just working on the on the
relationship between the toss arm and
the hitting arm
and that part is hard enough many people
struggle their lifetime with that
the toss is a very complex movement so
this is what we have to develop first
once you get comfortable we start using
the body later okay
lovely serve
see that toss not a bad serve but the
toss i'm dropped a little bit
too quickly do it again
better and you're finished by the pocket
and you know what that
you know what that was that's considered
an ace ace
so if you hit a serve super hard and you
hit it very close
to the lines the opponent can't touch it
that's called an ace
and that's what you just did you served
an ace did it feel good
yes yeah it felt good all right let's do
our racket tap
nice job
you